A Guide to the Isle of Wight County Museum Collection of P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company Records, 1860-1970
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Isle of Wight County Museum Collection of P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company Records, 1860-1970
The Library of Virginia
50200
30 reels
P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company (Isle of Wight County, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Loaned for microfilming by the Isle of Wight County Museum, Smithfield, Virginia.
Historical Information
In 1870, P. D. Gwaltney Sr. (1836-1915) moved from Surry County, Virginia, to Smithfield, Isle of Wight County, Virginia, and there established a retail and mercantile business, Gwaltney and Delk, with cousin O. G. Delk. Among other things, the business produced and sold a uniquely cured and smoked product called the "Smithfield Ham." The business became known as P. D. Gwaltney and Company in 1875, with Gwaltney retaining the store, smokehouse, shed, and wharf property. About 1880, he took on a partner to form Gwaltney, Chapman and Company. This partnership was dissolved in 1882.
P. D. Gwaltney Sr. and P. D. Gwaltney Jr. (1861-1936) then formed P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company, a retail and wholesale business dealing in dry goods, groceries, Smithfield Hams, liquor, fertilizers, and other items. Over time, the company began to focus solely on the curing and packing of pork. The company changed its name to Gwaltney Inc. in 1957, and then to ITT Gwaltney in 1970, when it was purchased by International Telephone and Telegraph, Inc. On 27 October 1981, the company became a subsidiary of Smithfield Foods, Inc., and the name was changed to Gwaltney of Smithfield, Ltd.
Scope and Content
Records, 1860-1970 of P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company and its predecessor and successor companies of Isle of Wight County, Virginia, consisting of account books, cash books, daybooks, encyclopedias, financial records, freight manifests, invoices, ledgers, letter books, minute books, stock lists, and other business records detailing the operations of P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company and its related firms. Collection also contains volumes of other businesses which worked with Gwaltney in its operations as well as other businesses in Isle of Wight County. Collection also contains an inventory of old homes in Isle of Wight County.
Contents List
- Isle of Wight County Museum Collection of P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company Records, 1860-1970 (Reel 6137-6143, 6158-6180)
  - P. D. Gwaltney ledger, 1860-1861, 1866-1867 (Reel 6137)
  - P. D. Gwaltney [Gwaltney and Delk?] account book, 1871 (Reel 6137)
  - Gwaltney [and Delk] [account?] book 3, 1871-1872 (Reel 6137)
  - Gwaltney and Delk account book, 1871-1872 (Reel 6137)
  - P. D. Gwaltney [Gwaltney and Delk?] account book, 1871-1875 (Reel 6137)
  - Gwaltney and Delk account book, 1872 (Reel 6138)
  - Gwaltney and Delk daybook, 1873 (Reel 6138)
  - Gwaltney and Delk daybook, 1873-1875 (Reel 6138)
  - P. D. Gwaltney store sales ledger, 1875-1878 (Reel 6139)
  - [P. D.] Gwaltney daybook, 1877-1878 (Reel 6139)
  - P. D. Gwaltney store sale ledger, 1878-1879 (Reel 6139)
  - P. D. Gwaltney ledger, 1879 (Reel 6140)
  - P. D. Gwaltney and Gwaltney, Chapman and Company store sales journal, 1879-1881 (Reel 6140)
  - P. D. Gwaltney and Gwaltney, Chapman and Company account book, 1879-1881 (Reel 6140)
  - Gwaltney, Chapman and Company and P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company account book, 1880-1882 (Reel 6140)
  - Gwaltney, Chapman and Company and P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company purchase invoices, 1881-1883 (Reel 6141)
  - Gwaltney, Chapman and Company and P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company purchase invoices, 1881-1883 (continued) (Reel 6142)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company invoices, 1883-1884 (Reel 6143)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1883-1884 (Reel 6158)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1884-1885 (Reel 6158)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1887-1888 (Reel 6159)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1888 (Reel 6160)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1889-1890 (Reel 6161)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1891-1892 (Reel 6162)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1892-1893 (Reel 6163)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company letter book, 1894-1897 (Reel 6164)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company correspondence regarding P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., residence, 1899-1901 (Reel 6165)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company stocks, 1893 (Reel 6165)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company stocks, 1900 (Reel 6165)
  - [P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company?] cashbook A, 1912-1914 (Reel 6165)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company meat product and sales record, peanut warehouse buying and storage record, 1918-1919 (Reel 6165)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company meat sales, 1928-1929 (Reel 6166)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company daily statement of business, 1932 (Reel 6166)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company daily statement of buisness, 1936 (Reel 6166)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company meat--sales/purchases/transfers/inventory, 1937 (Reel 6166)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company board of directors meeting minutes, 1929-1953 (Reel 6167)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company board of directors meeting minutes, 1953-1955 (Reel 6167)
  - P. D. Gwaltney, Jr., and Company and Gwaltney, Inc., board of directors meeting minutes, 1955-1962 (Reel 6167)
  - Gwaltney, Inc., board of directors meeting minutes, 1962-1967 (Reel 6168)
  - Gwaltney, Inc., board of directors meeting minutes, 1967-1970 (Reel 6168)
  - Gwaltney, Inc., mergert of Gwaltney, Inc., with and into ITT Gwaltney Inc., 1970 (Reel 6168)
  - Gwaltney Bunkley Peanut Company letter book, 1898 June-August (Reel 6169)
  - Gwaltney Bunkley Peanut Company letter book, 1898 August-October (target is mislabelled P. G. Gwaltney letter book, 1898) (Reel 6170)
  - Gwaltney Bunkley Peanut Company letter book, 1898-1899 (Reel 6171)
  - Gwaltney Bunkley Peanut Company letter book, 1899 May-July (Reel 6172)
  - Gwaltney Bunkley Peanut Company letter book, 1900 March-April (Reel 6173)
  - Sloop Two Sisters account book, 1868-1869 (Reel 6174)
  - Sloop Three Sisters manifest of freight, 1870-1871 (Reel 6175)
  - Sloop Three Sisters freight manifest, 1871-1873 (Reel 6175)
  - Sloop Three Sisters freight manifest, 1873-1874 (Reel 6175)
  - Smithfield Telephone Company record and toll book, 1894-1898 (Reel 6175)
  - [Smithfield Hardware Company?] ledger, 1915-1916 (Reel 6176)
  - [Smithfield Hardward Company?] ledger, ca. 1935 (Reel 6176)
  - A. C. Legg Packaging Company sales manual, undated (Reel 6176)
  - Unidentified cashbook, 1903-1908 (Reel 6177)
  - Unidentified policy ledger, 1904-1907 (Reel 6177)
  - Unidentified store ledger, 1905 (Reel 6177)
  - Unidentified store ledger, 1910 (Reel 6178)
  - Unidentified ledger, 1950-1955 (Reel 6178)
  - The Packer's Encyclopedia part three: Sausage and Meat Specialties, 1938 (Reel 6178)
  - Historical survey and inventory of old Isle of Wight houses, volume I undated (Reel 6179)
  - Historical surveys and inventory of old Isle of Wight houses, volume II, undated (Reel 6179)
  - P. D. Gwaltney and Gwaltney, Chapman and Company purchase invoices, 1880-1881 (Reel 6180)